Guide to the Stanford University, Department of Computer Science, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Department of Computer Science, records
1968-2007
SC0394
Stanford University. Computer Science Department.
3.75 Linear feet
Reports and memoranda concerning departmental rap sessions, 1968-69; memoranda, reports, diagrams, papers, and other materials, 1976-1981, pertaining to development of the SUN workstation, a network-based personal computer system designed at Stanford University; report on the Department, 1970; listing of personnel (staff, faculty, and students), 1971; files of Carolyn Tajnai, Director of the Stanford Computer Form, pertaining to Silicon Valley history and F. E. Terman, 1963-2007; class materials (syllabi, handouts, exams), 1962-84; reports on research in the department, 1967-69; Stanford Artificial Intelligence Laboratory Operating Notes, numbers 1-70 (incomplete set); "The Future of Computer Science at Stanford," by Forsythe, Herriot, and Miller, Feb. 1967; and Robert Floyd "Notes toward a revised formula ALGOL," 1966.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, 1990-1999
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Associated Materials
Twenty buttons from the Stanford Computer Forum are classed as AM 2008-013 in the Stanford University Archives Museum Collection.
Biographical/Historical note
The Department of Computer Science was established in 1965.
Description of the Collection
Reports and memoranda concerning departmental rap sessions, 1968-69; memoranda, reports, diagrams, papers, and other materials, 1976-1981, pertaining to development of the SUN workstation, a network-based personal computer system designed at Stanford University; report on the Department, 1970; listing of personnel (staff, faculty, and students), 1971; files of Carolyn Tajnai, Director of the Stanford Computer Form, pertaining to Silicon Valley history and F. E. Terman, 1963-2007; class materials (syllabi, handouts, exams), 1962-84; reports on research in the department, 1967-69; Stanford Artificial Intelligence Laboratory Operating Notes, numbers 1-70 (incomplete set); "The Future of Computer Science at Stanford," by Forsythe, Herriot, and Miller, Feb. 1967; and Robert Floyd "Notes toward a revised formula ALGOL," 1966.
Access Terms
Floyd, Robert W.; Forsythe, George E., (George Elmer), 1917-1972.; Stanford University. Computer Science Department.; Tajnai, Carolyn.; Computer networks.; Ethernet (Local area network system).; Microcomputer workstations.
Collection Contents
- Original accession
  Box 1 of the collection contains several different accessions. The first, accession number 1986-070, consists of reports and memoranda regarding departmental rap sessions, 1968-1969, which largely dealt with internal issues. The second accession, number 1990-186, concerns the development of the SUN workstation, a network-based personal computer system, and includes memoranda, reports, diagrams, papers, and other materials dating from 1976 to 1981. This accession was received as a notebook; the items have been removed and placed in folders, maintaining the original order. The third accession, number 1991-049, consists of two items that were part of a larger accession received from the Physics Library.
  Box 2 contains accession 2008-105, which appears to have been the files of Carolyn Tajnai, Director of the Stanford Computer Forum, and pertains to Silicon Valley history and F. E. Terman. Five boxes from accession 1999-102 were added to the collection in January 2010. They include class materials (syllabi, handouts, exams), 1962-84; reports on research in the department, 1967-69; Stanford Artificial Intelligence Laboratory Operating Notes, numbers 1-70 (incomplete set); "The Future of Computer Science at Stanford," by Forsythe, Herriot, and Miller, Feb. 1967; and Robert Floyd "Notes toward a revised formula ALGOL," 1966.
  - Dept. of Computer Science, Rap Sessions, 1968-69. Reports and memoranda. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - SUN WorkStation Hardware Projects: introductory material (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - File: pman, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - File: strm, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - File: pupser.doc, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - File: ARPA [SUN,AVB], 1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Data Link Layer Ethernet Interface, Overview and User Manual, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The SUN WorkStation Hardware Overview (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Network Graphics (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - SUN seminar information and minutes, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Trix Notes, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Computer Networking at Stanford; Current Status and Future Plans for Ethernet at Stanford University, 1980. Report by Ralph E. Gorin. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - ARPA proposal (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - SUN diagrams, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Press release, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Ethernet: Distributed Packet Switching for Local Computer Networks, 1976. Article by Robert M. Metcalfe and David R. Boggs. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Tools for Distributed Computing, 1980. Report by W.I. Nowicki. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The SUN WorkStation; A Terminal System for the Stanford University Network, 1980. Draft of report. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Perseus: Retrospective on a Portable Operating System, 1982. Report by Willy Zwaenepoel and Keith A. Lantz (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - The Implementation of Perseus as a Guest Level OS on the VAX 11/780, 1981. A report by Linda DeMichiel, Ginger Edighoffer, and Steve Kille. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Memory Sharing in a Distributed Processing Environment, 1980. A report by Jeffrey Mogul. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Perseus Disk Driver for IBM 3310 Disk, 1981. A report by R.F. McAllister. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Uniform Access to Resources in Perseus, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Report on Computer Science Department (memo from G.E. Forsythe to Computer Science Advisory Committee), 1970 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Personnel listing, 1971 (printout of file S623.PERSONNEL) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - ACME Notes, 1970-72 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Caddes, Carolyn, correspondence re her book Portraits of Success, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Computer Forum, correspondence of Carolyn Tajnai, 1982-97 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Computer Forum trivia (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, mostly of F.E. Terman with 2 regarding the Varian brothers and their company (most of these are prints of Stanford News Service images) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Research Park, clippings 1986-88 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - SITN – outline of a talk by Kenneth S. Down, 1982, and articles and clippings, 1977-83 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Tajnai, Carolyn, "Carolyn Tajnai’s Introduction to Computing," ca. 1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Tajnai, Carolyn, "Fred Terman, the Father of Silicon Valley," 1984-85 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Tajnai, Carolyn, two papers on Stanford and Silicon Valley, 1997, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Tajnai, Carolyn, notes (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Text of talks by F. E. Terman (photocopies), 1962-73 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Terman, F. E., articles, clippings, etc., 1963-84 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Materials on the history of Silicon Valley, 1974-93 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Magazine sources on the history of Silicon Valley (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Additional material, Accession ARCH-1999-102
  - Course materials
    - CS 5 course materials, 1962-64 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Notes for CS 136 and CS 5 by John G. Herriot, Sept. 1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - CS 5 course materials, Autumn 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - CS 5 course materials, Winter, Spring and Autumn 1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Notes for CS 136 and CS 5 by John G. Herriot, Sept. 1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - CS 136 / CS 5 course materials, Spring 1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - CS 5, Exams, 1963-65 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - CS 5, Exams, 1966-67 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - CS 5, Exams, 1968-70 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - CS 6, Exams, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - CS 6, Exams, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - CS 101 Readings, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - CS 101 Computers: Their Nature, Use, and Impact, student papers [no photocopies allowed], spring 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - CS 104, syllabus and assignments, Autumn 1971 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - CS 105 exams, 1970-71 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - CS 126 Class notes, September 1966 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - CS 126, Exams, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - CS 126/136, Exams, 1969-70 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Information on Stanford’s Systems and Languages: Notes for CS 135, Jan. 1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - CS 139 course materials, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - CS 139 course materials, 1966-67 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - CS 139 course materials, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - CS 139 exams, 1964-70 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - CS 142 class notes, Prof. Gio Wiederhold, Fall 1978 (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - CS 142 class notes, Prof. Gio Wiederhold, Fall 1978 (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - CS 142 / EE 285 class notes, winter 1982 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - CS 146 / EE 246 handouts, Fall 1982 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - CS 146 / EE 286 handouts, Winter 1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Readings in Artificial Intelligence, CS/Psych 224, Spring 1975 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - CS 231 course materials, 1965-67 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - CS 237 course materials, 1963-71 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - CS 237 exams, 1962-63 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - CS/Linguistics 266, class notes, Winter 1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - CS 343 / EE 483 class notes, spring 1981 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - EE/CS 701answers to homework, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Math 44 Homework Solutions 1984 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Math 116 solutions to assignments, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Math 130 Homework Solutions Winter 1984 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Math 232A Notes Autumn 1980 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Statistics 110 Past Exams 1964-65 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Dept. materials
    - The Future of Computer Science at Stanford, prepared by Forsythe, Herriot, and Miller, Feb. 1, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Research in the Computer Science Department Stanford University 1967 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Research in the Computer Science Department Stanford University April 26, 1968 (with remarks to the CS Advisory Committee by G. Forsythe, April 26, 1968) (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Research in the Computer Science Department Stanford University, April 21, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Artificial Intelligence Project memos, list of, ca. 1968 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Binder 1: Stanford Artificial Intelligence Laboratory Operating Notes #1 - #28 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Binder 2: Stanford Artificial Intelligence Laboratory Operating Notes #29 - #53 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Binder 3: Stanford Artificial Intelligence Laboratory Operating Notes #54 - #70 [incomplete] (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Computer Printout: Computer Science Library. Index to Uncatalogued Materials, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Computer Printout: Computer Science Library. Index to Uncatalogued Materials, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - George Forsythe: Proposal for renewal contract N00014-67-A-0112-0029 NR 044-211 (1969 and 1970) (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - George Forsythe, Numerical Analysis and Computer Science in Certain European and Soviet Centers, 26 July 1967 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Robert Floyd, "Notes toward a revised formula ALGOL," July 6, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - ISIS Demo [edited record for a hypothetical ISIS/0 usage session] 1970 (Box 5, Folder 4)